Have you ever wondered why is Chinese or not as famous as Japanese sword?
Almost everyone knows the word "katana"
But I bet not a lot of people know the
Chinese word for sword
to be honest I don't really know the reason why
China doesn't lack any fancy blades fictional or otherwise
So this video will just be an educated guess
A sneak peek in the philosophy of swords in China
And how swords are depicted on the silver screen
spoiler alert: I don't think China care much about swords
First let's set the stage
Sword myths similar to Excalibur and muramasa are not uncommon in China
The legendary swordsmith Gan Jiang and
Mo Ye is fairly well-known to the Chinese
In this legend the couple were
forced by an oppressive King in China
...to forge a sword
After the sword was finished
The king executed Gan Jiang, the husband
So that no more swords in the future can rival that of his
Still, another sword was forged in secret
The wife, Mo Ye, fled along with the sword and her unborn child
Hoping, one day, the son may seek vengeance against the king
It's a fairly standard legend about swords
the cinephiles among you may also remember the Green Destiny
In the film, it's often referred to as the sword of Li Mu Bai
Indeed, Chinese sword culture is not that different from that of Japanese
We both have the concept in which a sword is part of a person's identity
And we can recognize a person by the
sword
But there is a slight difference
In the scene from the Japanese film, Rurouni Kenshin 2
The villain explains that when two swordsman are equally skilled
Their weapons make the difference
The hero lost, because his sword is weaker
And as he puts it, the sword is his oath and faith
It symbolizes how his ideology is challenged
At the end, the hero wins the rematch by
finding a stronger sword
and having a stronger faith in the path he chose
Now, in the case of Green Destiny
The sword is indestructible, it can cut through other weapons with ease
But at the end, the weapons hardly matters
Fighting with a rusty sword
Fighting while grinding the sword
Winning a sword fight with a stick
In Chinese storytelling, a swordsman's skill is is often far more important than the weapon
in a Chinese novel "The Return of the Condor Heroes"
The strongest character, whom we only know by name and never actually met
...had reached a level so high, that he ended up using everyday objects as his weapon of choice
I believe this has something to do with kung fu and his focus in strengthen the body and mind
Over the utility of fighting and killing
In a sense, weapons are just someone's garment
You can recognize someone through it
but at the end, it's just a sharp piece of metal
it may also have something to do with Japanese Shinto beliefs
... that everyday things also have spirits within
In Japanese culture, swords may be sentient
but in Chinese Buddhist culture, however
Everything is an illusion
Ascending above material objects is a sign of enlightenment
Hence, the stick thing
Ultimately though, I don't think Chinese people care about swords  as much as other cultures
In the final battle of Jet Li's "Fearless"
The protagonist fights a Japanese martial
artist with weapons of their choosing
the Japanese martial artists, unsurprisingly, goes with a katana
The Chinese hero goes for a three-sectioned nunchuck
Which is technically a whip
The most recognizable Chinese weapon to the Chinese
... is probably Guandao
...a weapon of the Chinese god of war with
With the concept of "Eighteen Arms of Wushu" deeply rooted in Chinese culture
I think Chinese cinema simply prefers diversity
Swords
Spears
Paper Fans
Flying Guillotines
Threading needles
And Whatever Jackie Chan wants to use
Now, this is interesting...
No?